ATHM Textile Industry Stereographs 6524/006 P
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
- Series II: General Images Organized by Textile Related Subject
  - Roving (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Item 5: Speeders [Roving], Atlantic Cotton Mills, Lawrence, Mass. (Box 9, Folder 4)
      A. B. Hamor, ca. 1880. Black and white image shows rows of speeders, machinery which is one of the stages of the roving process. No workers visible. 17.75 x 10 cm.
    - Item 6: Inside a cotton mill at Malaga - spooling room and girl employees, Spain (Box 9, Folder 4)
      Black and white image shows rows of roving frames with spindles of thread. Female workers are posed by the front row of frames. Meadville, Pa.: Keystone View Company; copyrighted by Underwood and Underwood, ca. 1900-1920. 17.75 x 8.5 cm.
    - Item 7: Roving Frame manufactured by William Higgins & Sons, Manchester, England (Box 9, Folder 4)
      Black-and- white image shows male worker standing by a row of roving machines. He holds a spindle of thread in his right hand and a tool (?) of some sort in his left. Location of mill is unknown, but the plaque on the end of the row indicates the machinery was manufactured by Higgins & Sons of Manchester (Salford), England. ca. 1900. 17.5 x 10 cm.
    - Item 8: Harmony Mill No. 1, Cohoes, N.Y. - speeder, slubber and cards (Box 9, Folder 4)
      Black and white image shows rows of speeders and slubbers with carding machines in the background. Speeder is a term applied to the third machine in a series of roving frames; a slubber is the first of the roving frames in the cotton system. Albany, N.Y.: Haines, ca. 1870. 17 x 8 cm.
    - Item 9: "Speeders," where two strands are drawn and twisted together, White Oak Mills, Greensboro, N.C., 1907 (Box 9, Folder 4)
      Black and white image shows rows of speeders, a term used for the third machine in a series of roving frames. Roving frames reduce the size of the stock, even it, and insert a twist into it. Two female workers are seen operating the machinery. North Bennington, Vt.: H.C. White Co. 17.75 x 8.5 cm.
    - Item 10: Slubbing cotton yarn, Dallas Cotton Mills, Dallas Texas, 1905 (Box 9, Folder 4)
      Black and white image shows rows of slubbers, which is another term for the part of the roving process used in the cotton system of yarn manufacturing. Slubbing is the intermediary step between drawing and roving. Here a male worker is feeding sliver from cans into the frame where it is elongated, twisted, and wound upon bobbins. Meadville, Pa.: Keystone View Company. 17.75 x 8.5 cm.
    - Item 11: Slubbers in a Fall River [Mass.] Cotton Mill (Box 9, Folder 4)
      Color image shows two workmen, each standing by a row of slubbers. Slubbing is another term for part of the roving process in the cotton yarn system. Slubbers elongate the sliver and twist it into thread, which is then fed onto bobbins. Published by F.P. Charlton Co., Fall River, Mass. Printed in Germany. ca. 1907-1912. 14 x 9 cm.
    - Item 12: Roving frame - Silk Industry (Spun Silk), [Cheney Bros.], So. Manchester, Conn. (Box 9, Folder 4)
      Roving frame - Silk Industry (Spun Silk), [Cheney Bros.], So. Manchester, Conn. Black and white image shows a female operator working with the silk bobbins at the top of the frame, known as roving. The roving passes down over the machine in such a way that the fibers are twisted into threads by the spindles seen at the bottom of the frame. Although not specified here, this is the Cheney Bros. plant in South Manchester, Conn. Meadville, Pa.: Keystone View Company, ca. 1911-1915. 17.75 x 8.5 cm.
    - Item 13: Slubbers in a Fall River Cotton Mill [Fall River, Mass.], 1909 (Box 9, Folder 4)
      Color image of two male employees posing with slubbers. A slubber is the first of the roving frames used in the cotton system of yarn manufacturing. Specific mill is not identified. Published by F.P. Charlton Co., Fall River, Mass. Made in Germany. Postmarked Nov. 5, 1909 in Fall River. 14 x 9 cm.
    - Item 14: Cotton Roving Frames (Box 9, Folder 4)
      Black and white image shows a large room filled with cotton roving frames. No workers visible. Location unknown. ca. 1910-1918. 13.5 x 8.5 cm.
    - Item 15: Spinning silk - showing roving frame, [Cheney Bros.], So. Manchester, Conn. (Box 9, Folder 4)
      Black and white image shows a female worker adjusting fibers being fed through the roivng frame onto spindles. The roving passes down over the machine in such a way that the fibers are twisted into threads by the spindles seen at the bottom. Although not specified here, this is the Cheney Bros. plant in South Manchester, Conn. Meadville, Pa.: Keystone View Company, ca. mid-1920s. 18.75 x 8.75 cm.
    - Item 16: Roving Jute (Box 9, Folder 4)
      Black and white image shows rows of roving frames involving jute. Roving elongates and twists the sliver into thread and onto spindles. Note the roving cans clustered around the end of each set of machines. Carter's Series, No. 54. [Printed in Great Britain] [no earlier than 1902] 14 x 9 cm.
    - Item 17: Noon Hour in a Speeder Room of a Fall River Cotton Mill [Fall River, Mass.] (Box 9, Folder 4)
      Color image of a group of female employees posing near roving frames. Speeder is a term sometimes used for the third machine in a series of roving frames or for roving frames in general. Specific mill is not identified. Published by F.P. Charlton Co., Fall River, Mass. Made in Germany. ca .1907-1909. 14 x 9 cm.
    - Item 18: Woman in spinning room standing by roving cans. (Box 9, Folder 4)
      Gelatin silver print, ca. 1907-1910. Written on reverse: "This is Sarah Ramsbottom." Location is unidentified. 9 x 14 cm.
    - Item 19: Roving, Belfast, Ireland (Box 9, Folder 4)
      Black and white image shows rows of roving machinery. Possibly worsted roving on the Bradford system, but that has not been clearly identified. One male worker is in view. Labeled "Warping room, factory of the famous Irish linen, Belfast, Ireland," but this is clearly roving not warping. It is not totally clear if this is linen, although it would be unlikely that the publisher mistook the location of the image. See Items 20 and 21, in this folder, for copies of this image copyrighted by Underwood & Underwood. Meadville, Pa.: Keystone View Company, [after 1920]. 17.75 x 8.75 cm.
    - Item 20: Roving, Belfast, Ireland, 1903 (Box 9, Folder 4)
      Black and white image shows rows of roving machinery. Possibly worsted roving on the Bradford system, but that has not been clearly identified. One male worker is in view. Labeled "Warping room, factory of the famous Irish linen, Belfast, Ireland," but this is clearly roving not warping. It is not totally clear if this is linen, although it would be unlikely that the publisher mistook the location of the image. See Item 21, in this folder, for another copy of this image copyrighted by Underwood & Underwood. See Item 19, in this folder, for the Keystone View Company copy of this image. New York: Underwood & Underwood. 18 x 9 cm. Copy A.
    - Item 21: Roving, Belfast, Ireland, 1903 (Box 9, Folder 4)
      Black and white image shows rows of roving machinery. Possibly worsted roving on the Bradford system, but that has not been clearly identified. One male worker is in view. Labeled "Warping room, factory of the famous Irish linen, Belfast, Ireland," but this is clearly roving not warping. It is not totally clear if this is linen, although it would be unlikely that the publisher mistook the location of the image. Title printed on reverse in English, French, German, Spanish, Swedish, and Russian. See Item 20, in this folder, for another copy of this image copyrighted by Underwood & Underwood. See Item 19, in this folder, for the Keystone View Company copy of this image. New York: Underwood & Underwood. 18 x 9 cm. Copy B.
  - Spinning (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Item 1: Cucicartoni for jacquard pattern (Box 9, Folder 5)
      Museo didattico della Seta Como. Cucicartoni per disegni jacquard.Ph. Congiu/Farabolafoto - stampa Tip. Ed. Nami.
    - Item 2: Spinning and Weaving Woolen Shawls, Srinagar, Kashmir, India (Box 9, Folder 5)
      Black-and-white image depicts several Indian men working on a loom on the right, with an Indian woman squatting on the left in front of a spinning wheel, on which she is spinning goat hair into yarn. A number of men and boys look on at the left, while another man looks out the window of the dwelling on the right. Meadville, Pa.: Keystone View Company, ca. 1900- 1920. 17.75 x 8.75 cm.
    - Item 3: Martha Washington's Spinning Room, Mount Vernon, Virginia (Box 9, Folder 5)
      Color image of the spinning room, showing several spinning wheels and a loom in a room with a fireplace on the right-hand side. Printed on back of card: "Martha Washington's Spinning Room, Mt. Vernon, Va. The Spinning Room contains a valuable and interesting collection of spinning wheels and other paraphernalia of the industrious housewife of Martha Washington's day." Published by B. S. Reynolds Co., 1202 D. St., Northwest, Washington, D.C., ca. 1915-1930. 14 x 9 cm. See Item 57, in this folder, for the same image but a different publisher.
    - Item 4: Spinning Jenny (Hargreaves' design) (Box 9, Folder 5)
      Black and white image shows a male worker operating a spinning jenny. The spinning jenny was a spinning machine invented in 1764 by the English weaver James Hargreaves, and is usually credited with being the first practical machine for spinning cotton yarn. Postcard was originally printed for The West Yorkshire Folk Museum, Shibden Hall, Halifax [England]. That text has been lined through and replaced with "Textile Department, Bankfield Museum, Halifax [England]." ca. 1960s. 14 x 9 cm.
    - Item 5: Fileuse de la Haute-Savoie [Haute Savoie spinner] by Eugene Burgat (Box 9, Folder 5)
      Sepia-tone image reproduces painting by French painter Eugene Burgat, "Fileuse de la Haute-Savoie" in the Musee du Luxembourg, Paris. Haute-Savoie (Upper Savoy) is a region in eastern France, bordering both Switzerland and Italy. The image shows a woman feeding raw wool into a spinning wheel operated with a foot pedal. Bobbins and other related items are in the background. A Union Postale Universelle with "Post Card" printed on the reverse in English, French, German, Dutch, Italian, Spanish, and Russian. ca. 1920s. 8.75 x 13.75 cm.
    - Item 6: Pageant [Wo]men of Antrim, Sesqui-centennial, Antrim, New Hampshire, 1927 (Box 9, Folder 5)
      Black-and-white image of ten women posing outdoors, each with a spinning wheel. Four of the wheels are great wheels. Several of them are in Colonial dress. This was apparently part of Antrim's 150th anniversary. Handwritten on reverse side: "It was the custom of the early women to carry their wheels to a neighboring house, and spend the afternoon spinning and visiting together." Photo by E.D. Putnam & Son, Antrim, New Hampshire. 13.5 x 8.5 cm.
    - Item 7: Spinnstube a Fohr [Spinning at Fohr], 1902 (Box 9, Folder 5)
      Black and white image shows one woman hand carding wool on the left, while two others are spinning on spinning wheels. A man in the center is reading at a table. Appears to be photographed in a parlor or living area. Fohr is one of the North Frisian Islands on the German coast of the North Sea. Wilh. Muller, Photogr., Wyk. Postmarked 1902 in Dagebull (Germany). 14 x 9 cm.
    - Item 8: Young Shepherdess, painting by Jean-Francois Millet, French (1814-1875), 1984 (Box 9, Folder 5)
      Color reproduction of painting shows a young woman holding a distaff with (probably) wool in her left hand and an implement in her right. Original painting gift of Samuel Dennis Warren, 1877, to the Museum of Fine Arts, Boston. Boston, Mass.: Museum of Fine Arts, Boston. Postmarked April 30, 1984. 11 x 15.25 cm.
    - Item 9: Grandmother works with distaff as little boy looks on in Greece (Box 9, Folder 5)
      Color image shows woman old enough to be a grandmother, working fibers through a distaff as a little boy looks on. Both are pictured by a fireplace; the grandmother is seated in a chair as she works; the boy is seated on the floor looking up at her. Printed in Greece by M. Toumbis. ca. 1970. 14.5 x 10 cm.
    - Item 10: The Thread Maker, Spain, 1966 (Box 9, Folder 5)
      Black and white image shows a woman in the foreground, spinning thread using a distaff. She is shown running the thread through her teeth. Another woman works in the background, possibly sewing. Original photograph by W. Eugene Smith, 1950. From the photography collection of The Museum of Modern Art. Printed in Western Germany. Date stamped Aug. 11 1966 on reverse, but card was probably manufactured between 1950 and 1962. 10.5 x 14.75 cm.
    - Item 11: Display of hand textile machinery at Deerfield, Mass., 1921 (Box 9, Folder 5)
      Black and white image shows two rows of spinning machinery, including several spinning wheels, a winder, and a variety of other early textile machinery on display in Deerfield, Mass. A vertical jenny can be seen at the right of the image. "Russell Kittell Jany 8. 1921" written on reverse of card. Card was most likely produced between 1918 and 1922. 14 x 9 cm.
    - Item 12: Spinning wheels, reel, and other implements, 1906 (Box 9, Folder 5)
      Black and white image shows several textile-related implements photographed in an [unknown] outside setting. They include a great wheel, a spinning wheel, and a reel (on the left) that would wind yarn into skeins. Dated by hand 10-3-12, but this style of postcard was manufactured only in 1906. Penn. mailing address but card was never stamped and mailed. Dated by hand 11/18/06, in the stamp area. 14 x 8.5 cm.
    - Item 13: Sitting Room, Betsy Williams Cottage, Roger Williams Park, Providence, R.I., 1909 (Box 9, Folder 5)
      Color image of wallpapered room with fireplace. Cooking implements and a bellows are in the fireplace opening. By the fireplace is a spinning wheel and an infant's cradle. A.C. Bosselman & Co., New York. Printed in Germany. Postmarked May 3, 1909 in Providence. 14 x 9 cm.
    - Item 14: Spinning wheel and Pilgrim relics, Plymouth, Mass. (Box 9, Folder 5)
      Black and white image shows wooden spinning wheel, a candlestick, and a woman's shoe. Photographed by W.S. Robbins & Co., Plymouth, Mass. One in the "Plymouth Series." ca. 1870s. 17.5 x 8.75 cm.
    - Item 15: Industry and simplicity--interior of a Switzer's mountain home--Saas-fee, Switzerland, 1901 (Box 9, Folder 5)
      Black and white image shows a woman working wool fibers into strands of thread on a wooden spinning wheel. The room is constructed with a wooden ceiling, floor, and walls. Religious pictures hang on the walls. New York: Underwood & Underwood. 17.75 x 8.5 cm.
    - Item 16: Gov. Carver's chair; ancient spinning wheel, Pilgrim Hall, Plymouth, Mass. (Box 9, Folder 5)
      Color image shows wooden chair with dowels on the back and arms next to a wooden spinning wheel. Copyrighted and published by A. S. Burbank, Plymouth Mass. "Phostint"made only by Detroit Publishing Co. ca. 1930. 14 x 9 cm.
    - Item 17: Spinning wheel (great wheel) in front of a fireplace., 1949 (Box 9, Folder 5)
      Black and white image shows great wheel by a wood-burning brick fireplace. A table and chair are also visible. No location given. Postmarked Dec. 1949 in Boston, Mass. 13.75 x 8.75 cm.
    - Item 18: Moorland Cottage interior, Castle Museum, York, England (Box 9, Folder 5)
      The Folk Museum of Yorkshire Life. Black and white image of a bedroom, representative of a moorland cottage, probably Victorian era. Ornate, almost cluttered, display of vases, pictures, table and chairs. On the left is a four-poster bed with a canopy. Near the hearth lies a dog, and chairs, a cradle, and a spinning wheel are visible. Photo, Catchesides, York. Copyright of Castle Museum, York. Published by Harvey Barton of Bristol, Ltd. ca. 1960s. 14 x 9 cm.
    - Item 19: Spinning wool at Murray Bay, P.Q. [Province of Quebec, Canada] (Box 9, Folder 5)
      Black and white image shows an elderly woman working at a wooden spinning wheel on the right. A man stands next to her in front of an open door. Tools and kitchen utensils hang on the walls behind them. The scene is possibly taking place on an outside porch or shed. Published by Novelty Manufacturing & Art Co., Ltd., Montreal. ca. 1912-1926. 14 x 8.75 cm.
    - Item 20: Italian 18th-century spinning wheel at Victoria & Albert Museum, London (Box 9, Folder 5)
      Color image shows decorative wooden spinning wheel adorned with marquetry of tortoiseshell, mother-of-pearl, and ivory. The piece was probably designed more for decoration than for spinning. Given to V & A by the Hon. Mrs. Carpenter. Photograph copyright Fratellli Fabbri; printed in England. ca. 1970. 10.5 x 15 cm.
    - Item 21: Spinning wheel, Le Rouet, Quebec, Canada (Box 9, Folder 5)
      Color image shows an elderly woman working at a spinning wheel on her porch. A young boy sits in the doorway watching her. "Canadian Art Deeptone" Series, made in Canada. ca. 1930. 14 x 8.5 cm.
    - Item 22: Asian woman working at spinning wheel (Box 9, Folder 5)
      Black and white image shows a woman working at a spinning wheel in front of a brick wall. A large ball of unknown fiber is in the background by the wall. The spinning wheel itself appears to be made of thin sticks and wire, as opposed to the traditional wooden spinning wheel. Unknown location. ca. 1910-1917. 13.75 x 8.5 cm.
    - Item 23: At grandmother's house--interior of a Breton village home, Crach, France (Box 9, Folder 5)
      Black and white image shows an elderly woman at a spinning wheel by the fireplace hearth. The room appears to serve multiple purposes with cooking utensils at the hearth and a bed built into a wall on the right, with curtains to draw at bedtime. New York: Underwood & Underwood, ca. 1900-1920. 18 x 9 cm
    - Item 24: Native Boys Spinning Cotton, Egypt (Box 9, Folder 5)
      Black and white image shows a scene in the desert with a row of spinning wheels and two boys working at each to spin cotton into threads for the manufacture of Egyptian cotton. The spinning wheels seen here are much cruder than those used in the 1800s, and require two persons to use one wheel. One turns the wheel while the other draws out the thread. In the background, what appears to be stones are piles of cotton ready for spinning. Meadville, Pa.: Keystone View Co., ca. 1900-1920. 18 x 9 cm.
    - Item 25: Bergers Landais tricotant et filant au vrouet [Landais shepherds knitting and spinning the wheel], 1946 (Box 9, Folder 5)
      Black and white image shows an outdoor scene with one man spinnning on a small spinning wheel, and two looking on. Two of the men are wearing coats made of animal fur (perhaps wool) and the third man is carrying a bag that is also made of fur. A dog sits by the spinner. Landes is a region in southwest France. Carte Postale. Postmarked April 16, 1946 in Landes? 14 x 9 cm.
    - Item 26: Anna Codde, portrait by Maerten van Heemskerck (1498-1574) (Box 9, Folder 5)
      Color image of a portrait of Anna Codde, by Maerten van Heemskerck, showing a woman spinning thread at a spinning wheel. Original painting in The Rijksmuseum, Amsterdam, The Netherlands. [after 1948] 10.5 x 15 cm.
    - Item 27: Natives Spinning Coir Yarn (Box 9, Folder 5)
      Black and white image shows a man using a manual spinning machine on the far left. Other men are standing in line with raw material ready to be spun. The scene is outdoors and palm trees are in the background. Coir is the fiber obtained from the outer husk of the Indian or Cingalese cocoanut. The coarser stock is used in brushes; the better quality in rope and cocoa matting. Based on the dress of the men and the scenery, this scene is most likely in India. Carter's Series No. 27. [Printed in Britain.] [no earlier than 1902] 13.75 x 8.75 cm.
    - Item 28: Spinning wheel, brought over in the Mayflower (Box 9, Folder 5)
      Black and white image depicts spinning wheel in front of curtain backdrop. No location given. Littleton, New Hampshire: Photographed and published by B. W. Kilburn, ca. 1890s. 18 x 10.5 cm.
    - Item 29: "Why don't you speak for yourself, John?" (Box 9, Folder 5)
      Color image depicts Priscilla Mullen sitting at a spinning wheel in early Plymouth, Mass., with John Alden kneeling by her side. Very similar to Item 78, in this folder. Copyrighted and published by A. S. Burbank, Plymouth, Mass. Phostint trademark made only by Detroit Publishing Co. "July 30 / 1921" written on reverse of card. ca. 1915-1921. 9 x 14 cm.
    - Item 29: Pont-Aven [France] - Devant le Lit clos [Before the box bed] (Box 9, Folder 5)
      Black and white image depicts a young woman on the left, a young girl in the middle, and a young man on the right, all standing behind a spinning wheel with a distaff of flax fibers, and looking at a magazine. In the background is an elaborately carved wooden piece, which may be the "box bed" referred to in the title. Pont-Aven is in Brittany, and all three are dressed in elaborate costumes suggesting Breton dress. A verse by Botrel (most likely Jean-Baptiste-Theodore-Marie Botrel, a native of Brittany) is printed at the bottom of the card: "Durant que l'on veille, Le Bon Dieu surveille, Le grain quui sommeille, Au coeur des Guerets." [During that one day before, the good God monitors, the dormant grain, in the heart of the fields.] [Published by] Laurent-Nel, Rennes [Brittany]. [no earlier than 1904] 9 x 14 cm.
    - Item 30: German family working with flax wheels, 1913 (Box 9, Folder 5)
      Color image depicts four women, one man, and a little boy, each working by hand with flax pulled from distaffs. Two spinning wheels are visible; the little boy appears to be working with a winder. The interior setting seems to be within a home with many photographs and prints hanging on the walls of the room. Stamped with the name of a hotel on the reverse in Donauschingen, a town in the Black Forest [Schwarzwald] area of Germany. J. G. Fleig, Photogr., Kunstverlag, Hornberg [Germany]. Dated by hand July 18, 1913; message written in German. Postmarked in Donauschingen. 13.5 x 8.75 cm.
    - Item 31: "The Gossips," illustrated by F. R. Smith, 1921 (Box 9, Folder 5)
      Black-and-white image (slightly tinted) shows two women in colonial costume seated by a spinning wheel." Appears to be an illustration of a watercolor (?) titled The Gossips," by F. R. Smith. On reverse of card: "Presented by The Duxbury Shop, Miss E. M. Leete, Prop., Duxbury, Mass." A Longfellow poem relating to spinning is also printed on the reverse. May have been used for promotional purpose: Published by Geo. E. Keith Company, Makers of Walk-Over Shoes. Logo bottom right corner of front illustration depicts a woman and a shoe. Dated by hand July 30, 1921. 14 x 9 cm.
    - Item 32: Great Wool Wheel and smaller spinning wheel in woodland setting (Box 9, Folder 5)
      Black and white image depicts a woman standing by a great wheel, and a man sitting down behind the edge of the great wheel in what appears to be a posed situation, as they are in a wooded setting, surrounded by trees and ferns. A smaller spinning wheel is in the foreground. No location given. ca. 1900. 17.5 x 8.75 cm.
    - Item 33: Irish flax wheel (Box 9, Folder 5)
      Black and white image depicts an Irish flax wheel for spinning flax. Textile Department, Bankfield Museum, Halifax [Yorkshire, England]. Formerly a private residence, Bankfield was sold in 1887 and was transformed into a museum. ca. 1950-1962. 8.75 x 14 cm.
    - Item 34: Flax wheel, "In a Snarl" (Box 9, Folder 5)